Hari Sharma fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
- Correspondence, 1969 - 2009; F-251-2; 74 cm of textual records; Language: Some correspondence and notes in Hindi.
  - India Civil Rights / Human Rights of Minority Groups and Grassroot Organizations, 1986 - 1988; F-251-2-0-0-76 (Artifact box - large 251-70)
  - Other Groups, 1986 - 1988; F-251-2-0-0-77 (Artifact box - large 251-70)
  - Misc. Political Activists - India, 1973 - 1975; F-251-2-0-0-78 (Artifact box - large 251-70)
  - Punjab / Himachal, 1977 - 1978; F-251-2-0-0-79 (Artifact box - large 251-70)
  - Gail Omvedt, 1969 - 1984; F-251-2-0-0-80 (Artifact box - small 251-71)
  - North American friends (academics) - 1, 1977 - 1988; 251-2-0-0-81 (Artifact box - large 251-71)
  - North American friends academics - 2, 1974 - 1988; 251-2-0-0-82 (Artifact box - large 251-71)
  - Sawraj Singh, 1975 - 1978; 251-2-0-0-83 (Artifact box - small 251-71)
  - South Asian People's Organisation (SAPO) and India forum, 1977 - 1978; F-251-2-0-0-84 (Artifact box - small 251-71)
  - Ved P. Duggal, 1977 - 1985; F-251-2-0-0-85 (Artifact box - small 251-71)
  - Leila Fernandes, 1976 - 1977; F-251-2-0-0-86 (Artifact box - small 251-71)
  - Talk tour - Jan-Feb 1975, F-251-2-0-0-87 (Artifact box - small 251-71)
  - Gautam Appa, 1974 - 1988; F-251-2-0-0-88 (Artifact box - large 251-72)
  - Ranajit Guha, 1976 - 1984; F-251-2-0-0-89 (Artifact box - large 251-72)
  - Dilip Dutt, 1974 - 1989; F-251-2-0-0-90 (Artifact box - large 251-72)
  - Africa / Asia / Australia, 1974 - 1988; F-251-2-0-0-91 (Artifact box - large 251-72)
  - Middle East, 1981 - 1982; F-251-2-0-0-92 (Artifact box - large 251-72)
  - Europe, 1975 - 1988; F-251-2-0-0-93 (Artifact box - large 251-72)
  - Europe, 1973 - 1974; F-251-2-0-0-94 (Artifact box - large 251-72)
  - Sweden, 1977 - 1987; F-251-2-0-0-95 (Artifact box - large 251-72)
  - Denmark, 1976 - 1988; F-251-2-0-0-96 (Artifact box - large 251-72)
  - Charan Singh, 1976 - 1988; F-251-2-0-0-97 (Artifact box - large 251-72)
  - France, 1976 - 1988; F-251-2-0-0-98 (Artifact box - large 251-72)
  - Maria Mies, 1975 - 1976; F-251-2-0-0-99 (Artifact box - large 251-72)
  - Amnesty International, 1975 - 1988; F-251-2-0-0-100 (Artifact box - large 251-72)
    Open, no restrictions
    Access review (Mar 2, 2023) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
- Community activism records, 1968 - 2008; F-251-3; 4.12 m of textual records
  Series consists of records arising from Hari Sharma's community activism work that includes helping to mobilize people toward the formation of the Indian People's Association of North America (IPANA) through his leadership, writings, and talks; systematically addressing racism in British Columbia through his committee work with the British Columbia Organization to Fight Racism (BCOFR); standing in solidarity with Indo-Canadian farmworkers in the Fraser Valley and members of IPANA in the formation of the Canadian Farmworkers Union; uniting IPANA with other groups in the community to form the Komagata Maru Historical Society with the impending 75th anniversary of the Komagata Maru incident in 1989; playing a leadership role in the creation of Non-Resident Indians for Secularism and Democracy (NRISAD) when IPANA faded away, and then helping NRISAD expand its focus to the entire South Asian region as it evolved into the South Asian Network for Secularism and Democracy (SANSAD); building relationships with members of the Secwepemc (Shuswap) Nation in south-central B.C. as co-chair of the SCES/SFU partnership; and defending human rights and social justice, often providing expert witness testimony in immigration and Workers' Compensation Board (WCB) claim cases within the South Asian community. Series includes the organizational records of BCOFR, IPANA, and NRISAD-SANSAD; interviews, transcripts, case files, notes, and correspondence.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist and based on the names of organizations documented in the records. Files are arranged chronologically.
  - British Columbia Organization to Fight Racism files, 1973 - 1990; F-251-3-1; 38 cm of textual records; Language: Some notes in Hindi.; British Columbia Organization to Fight Racism
    The British Columbia Organization to Fight Racism (BCOFR) was founded in November 1980, with the core leadership and the majority of its membership from the Indi-Canadian community in Vancouver. Many of the founders were also members of the Indian People's Assocation in North America (IPANA). The organization drew members from different communities and traversed ethnic and class lines. At its peak, BCOFR had close to 1,500 members, and its leadership consisted of a president, executive committee, and task-oriented committees. Some of BCOFR's activities included producing a newsletter and organizing social and educational activities to promote community awareness of racism. In addition, BCOFR petitoned, rallied, and campaigned against discriminatory immigration practices.
    Sub-series consists of records arising from Hari Sharma's investigative and research activities into racism in British Columbia while serving on the British Columbia Organization to Fight Racism (BCOFR) Executive Committee as a founding member and as Chairperson of the organization's Investigation and Support Committee. Includes demonstration flyers, notes, contact lists, minutes, newsletters, agendas, newspaper clippings, correspondence, memos, notices, and a pledge book.
    British Columbia Organization to Fight Racism; Textual records
    - Indians in Vancouver, 1973 - 1980; F-251-3-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 251-17)
    - Facist Attack By CPL(ML) Disrupts IPANA Demonstration, 1976; F-251-3-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 251-17)
    - Bill C-24 - notes and contacts, 1977 - 1978; F-251-3-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 251-17)
    - Immigration Committee, 1977 - 1978; F-251-3-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 251-17)
    - Committee to Fight Racism - K. Samra meeting, 1980; F-251-3-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 251-17)
    - BCOFR Executive Meeting - May 1981 - Jan 1983 (I AGM - II AGM), 1981 - 1983; F-251-3-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 251-17)
    - Anti-Klan Coalition, 1981 - 1982; F-251-3-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 251-17)
    - BCOFR Investigation Committee - closed cases, 1981 - 1982; F-251-3-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 251-17)
      Restricted in whole
    - Investigation Committee (misc.), 1981 - 1982; F-251-3-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 251-17)
      Restricted in part
    - Zionism, 1981 - 1982; F-251-3-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 251-17)
    - BCOFR Membership and Contacts, [ca 1981] - [ca 1983]; F-251-3-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 251-17)
      Open, reading room
      Access review (Jan 10, 2023) – File includes records that contain some individuals' personal contact information. File can be accessed in the Archives' reading room, but documents containing contact information cannot be photographed and will be redacted in any digital access copies made by Archives.
    - BCOFR Investigation Committee - meeting minutes, supporting documents, 1981 - 1988; F-251-3-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 251-17)
    - ABM Co., 1982 - 1983; F-251-3-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 251-18)
      Access review (Jan 10, 2023) – File includes records that contain the personal information of identifiable individuals (third party opinions about individual, employment history, race). The file is restricted in whole, but may be accessed under a Research Agreement; consult the reference archivist for more information.
    - BCOFR pledge book, 1982 - 1983; F-251-3-1-0-14 (Archival box - standard 251-18)
    - BCOFR Investigation Committee - current cases (notes, correspondence), 1982 - 1984; F-251-3-1-0-15 (Archival box - standard 251-18)
    - BCOFR Executive Meetings, 1983 - 1985; F-251-3-1-0-16 (Archival box - standard 251-18)
    - BCOFR Newsleter Committee, 1983 - 1989; F-251-3-1-0-17 (Archival box - standard 251-18)
    - BCOFR Anti-Racism Education and Research Society, 1985 - 1987; F-251-3-1-0-18 (Archival box - standard 251-18)
    - BCOFR membership list, [ca 1985] - [ca 1989]; F-251-3-1-0-19 (Archival box - standard 251-18)
    - BCOFR Newsletter (non-continuous), 1981 - 1989; F-251-3-1-0-20 (Archival box - standard 251-18)
    - BCOFR AGM (membership list, agendas, minutes, notes), 1986 - 1988; F-251-3-1-0-21 (Archival box - standard 251-19)
    - Investigation and Support Committee, 1987 - 1989; F-251-3-1-0-22 (Archival box - standard 251-19)
    - BCOFR 1988 (from March 1988 AGM), 1988 - 1989; F-251-3-1-0-23 (Archival box - standard 251-19)
    - BCOFR Extended Meeting, 1989 - 1990; F-251-3-1-0-24 (Archival box - standard 251-19)
    - BCOFR 1989, 1989 - 1990; F-251-3-1-0-25 (Archival box - standard 251-19)
    - BCOFR Funds Appeal, 1989; F-251-3-1-0-26 (Archival box - standard 251-19)
    - BCOFR Eighth AGM, 1989; F-251-3-1-0-27 (Archival box - standard 251-19)
    - CRJ seminar, 1989 - 1990; F-251-3-1-0-28 (Archival box - standard 251-19)
    - BCOFR 1989-1990 Executive, F-251-3-1-0-29 (Archival box - standard 251-19)
    - NACOI, BC Chapter (work with BCOFR), 1990; F-251-3-1-0-30 (Archival box - standard 251-19)
  - Canadian Farmworkers Union interviews and transcripts, 1979 - 2004; F-251-3-2; 13 cm of textual records; Language: Some notes in Hindi.; Canadian Farmworkers Union
    On February 26, 1979, after a series of casual meetings, Raj Chouhan, Harinder Mahil, and Charan Gill formed the Farm Workers’ Organizing Committee (FWOC) in the Fraser Valley of British Columbia. They were joined at this first official meeting by Sarwan Sidhu, Pritam Singh, Amarit Pal Mann, and Gurnam Sahota. Sarwan Boal and Judy Cavanagh soon joined the FWOC as organizers. A series of public meetings followed to spread awareness of the new group, address farmworkers’ concerns, and advocate for their rights. In the spring of 1980, at a founding convention, members of the FWOC formally established the Canadian Farmworkers Union (CFU). Chouhan was president, Jawala Singh Grewal was vice-president, Gill was secretary, and Boal was treasurer. Cavanagh was a chief organizer. The motto of the CFU was “Zindabad!” (“Long live!” in Urdu). Areas of concern and action for this new union included farmworkers’ pay, housing, working conditions, and work-related legislation. The CFU advocated for childcare for farmworkers and raised awareness of the racism the predominantly Indo-Canadian workers often faced, and also participated in numerous rights-related events and causes in solidarity with other organizations. The CFU was assisted financially by the Canadian Labour Congress (CLC) from founding until 1991.
    In 1979 the FWOC began publishing The Farmworker, a Punjabi/English newspaper with the purpose of educating workers about their rights on the job and their right to organize. The CFU continued publishing this paper through the mid-1990s.
    In the early 1980s the CFU focused on recruiting members and gaining certification at some farms, and also picketed and fought in court to defend farmworkers’ right to unionize and to protect workers from mistreatment by farm owners. In November of 1980, the collective agreement signed by the CFU and Bell Farms was the first ever signed by a union representing farmworkers in Canada. The union was also particularly vocal about the exclusion of farmworkers from various legislation protecting other workers’ rights and safety. In 1983, farmworkers became eligible for Workers’ Compensation Board benefits, but were still mainly exempt from health and safety regulations.
    In its early years, the CFU tried to organize farmworkers outside the Fraser Valley and Lower Mainland, reaching out to workers in the BC Okanagan and Ontario. It did not succeed in the Okanagan, due to conflict between CFU executives and local organizers, and in Ontario its success lasted only a few years.
    In addition to its unionization and advocacy work, the CFU responded to its membership’s needs with relevant educational programming. In 1982 the union began running “ESL Crusade” classes, developed specifically for Punjabi-speaking farmworkers and including both everyday and farmwork-specific English lessons. The “preventable homicide” of worker Jarnail Singh Deol by pesticide exposure led to the establishment of the Deol Agricultural Education and Research Society (the Deol Society) in 1983, as an internal branch of CFU created for the purpose of applying separately from the union for funding grants. The Deol Society’s main concern was education of farmworkers on the health risks and safe handling of pesticides, and it also ran ESL programs. In many projects, jurisdiction was shared by the Deol Society and the CFU.
    The CFU researched a wide variety of subjects related to farmworkers and workers in general, in order to educate its members and spread awareness of many issues, from global struggles for workers’ and women’s rights to immigration and multiculturalism in Canada. CFU executives and members participated in union, labour, and activist groups and committees, and were vocal in numerous letter-writing, fundraising, and awareness campaigns. The union also participated in rallies and protests on many subjects.
    By the mid-1980s the CFU was nearly bankrupt due to the ongoing difficulty of collecting dues from underpaid seasonal workers. The union briefly considered merging with other similar unions but, convinced of the unique needs of its membership, it was determined to retain its own name.
    In 1986, Chouhan stepped down, principal organizer Judy Cavanagh and founding member Charan Gill left, and Sarwan Boal became president. Boal was replaced in 1991 by Jawala Singh Grewal.
    In the 1990s, the provincial New Democratic Party government extended health and safety legislation to farmworkers, solving one of the CFU’s main areas of concern. The Progressive Intercultural Community Services Society (PICS, formerly Progressive Indo-Canadian Community Services Society) and its founder, Charan Gill, took over management of the union and its work. The CFU still exists in name, but is essentially inactive.
    Sub-series consists of records arising from Hari Sharma's research into institutional racism in the workplace and focuses on farm labour in British Columbia where labour migrations (from South Asia and elsewhere) have created a multiracial working class. Includes questionnaires, responses, notes, memos, membership campaign materials, and articles written by Sharma.
    Canadian Farmworkers Union; Textual records; Sound recordings
    - Speech by the president of the Farm Workers' organizing committee, 1979; F-251-3-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 251-20)
    - Farmworkers Questionnaire, 1981; F-251-3-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 251-20)
    - Research - farmworkers, 1981; F-251-3-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 251-20)
    - Responses to Farmworkers Questionnaire: A-Z, 1981; F-251-3-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 251-20)
    - Responses to Farmworkers Questionnaire: 1-30, 1981; F-251-3-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 251-20)
    - Race and class in B.C.: The Case of B.C.'s Farmworkers, An interview with Hari Sharma, [ca 1981] - [ca 1983]; F-251-3-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 251-20)
    - CFU (membership campaign materials), 1984; F-251-3-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 251-20)
    - Notes associated with F-77, Indo-Canadian Oral History collection interviewees, 2004; F-251-3-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 251-20)
  - Indian People's Association in North America files, 1973 - 1995; F-251-3-3; 74 cm of textual records; Language: Some notes in Hindi. Also contains publications in Punjabi and French.; Indian People's Association in North America
    The Indian People's Association in North America (IPANA) was founded on June 25, 1975 as a patriotic organization of Indians living in North America. IPANA established chapters throughout North Amerioca in an effort to oppose imperialism and to promote democratic rights and social justic in India.
    Sub-series consists of records arising from Hari Sharma's involvement with the founding of the Indian People's Association in North America (IPANA) in Montréal and his active participation in the Vancouver chapter. Sharma helped to produce IPANA's three publications: quarterly New India Bulletin which came out of Montréal from 1975, India Now, a monthly that was produced in New York from 1976, and Wangar, a Punjabi paper that was produced from Vancouver every two months from 1977. He also supported the focus of IPANA's work (in defense of minority rights and the principles of secular democracy in India through engagement with issues concerning the local South Asian community in their own daily lives) by helping to organize public meetings, demonstrations, lectures, films, educational study groups, and cultural programs. As Chairman of the Vancouver unit, Sharma brought together IPANA and other groups in Vancouver with their own liberation struggles to create a culture of solidarity of people's struggles that eventually led to the formation of the Third World People's Coalition (TWPC). IPANA also intervened successfully in working class struggles and in support of women facing violence within the South Asian community. Through the 1980s, IPANA dedicated its energies to the development of the Canadian Farmworkers Union and the anti-racist work undertaken by the British Columbia Organization to Fight Racism (BCOFR). Collectively, these organizations helped unite multi-ethnic communities, unions, religious groups, First Nations, students, and others in opposition to the spread of racism, hatred, and violence. Sub-series includes memos, notes, articles, correspondence, statements, minutes, press releases, reports, resolutions, contact lists, event announcements, and other publicity materials.
    Indian People's Association in North America; New India Bulletin; Wangar; Third World People's Coalition; Textual records
    - NIB (after Feb '76 meetup, Toronto), [ca 1976]; F-251-3-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 251-21)
    - New India Bulletin (annotated drafts of articles, publications, notes, correspondence), 1976 - 1979; F-251-3-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 251-21)
    - India Now (memos, notes re. articles), 1980 - 1984; F-251-3-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 251-21)
    - IPANA - responses to bulletins and issues, 1983 - 1984; F-251-3-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 251-21)
    - India Abroad (vol. 14, nos. 13, 16), 1983 - 1984; F-251-3-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 251-21)
    - Wagnar, vols. 7-8, 1985; F-251-3-3-0-6 (Archival box - standard 251-21)
    - Wagnar, vol. 8, no. 1, Oct 1987, F-251-3-3-0-7 (Archival box - standard 251-21)
    - Wagnar, vol. 87, no. 2, Nov-Dec 1987 - 5 copies, F-251-3-3-0-8 (Archival box - standard 251-21)
    - Internal Bulletins: July 1975-March 1980, 1975 - 1980; F-251-3-3-0-9 (Archival box - standard 251-22)
    - Internal Bulletins: 23-27, 30, 1980 - 1984; F-251-3-3-0-10 (Archival box - standard 251-22)
    - Internal Bulletin 28 - issues, correspondence, notes, 1983 - 1984; F-251-3-3-0-11 (Archival box - standard 251-22)
    - Internal Bulletins: 29-32, 1983 - 1984; F-251-3-3-0-12 (Archival box - standard 251-22)
    - South Asia Committee - misc., 1973 - 1974; F-251-3-3-0-13 (Archival box - standard 251-23)
    - IPANA: August 1976 Convention misc. documents (extra copies), 1975 - 1976; F-251-3-3-0-14 (Archival box - standard 251-23)
    - Vancouver Unit, 1975 - 1976; F-251-3-3-0-15 (Archival box - standard 251-23)
    - IPANA: Toronto Meeting (February 1976), F-251-3-3-0-16 (Archival box - standard 251-23)
    - Third World People's Coalition, 1976; F-251-3-3-0-17 (Archival box - standard 251-23)
    - CPC-ML attack, August 14, 1976, F-251-3-3-0-18 (Archival box - standard 251-23)
    - IPANA: August '76 convention documents, 1976; F-251-3-3-0-19 (Archival box - standard 251-23)
    - August Convention: IPANA Solidarity Statements, 1976; F-251-3-3-0-20 (Archival box - standard 251-23)
    - Open letters to S.C. Dube (Indian Sociological Society), 1976 - 1977; F-251-3-3-0-21 (Archival box - standard 251-23)
    - IPANA: New York Meeting, 1976 - 1977; F-251-3-3-0-22 (Archival box - standard 251-23)
    - TWAICC (Third World Anti-Imperialist Coordinating Committee), 1976 - 1978; F-251-3-3-0-23 (Archival box - standard 251-23)
    - Vancouver Unit, 1976 - 1978; F-251-3-3-0-24 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - IPANA contacts in B.C., 1976 - 1979; F-251-3-3-0-25 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - ALLIANCE - proposal, 1977; F-251-3-3-0-26 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - East Indian Workers Association (EIWA), 1977; F-251-3-3-0-27 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - Chin and Aruna Banerjee: A Note for IPANA Convention, [ca 1977]; F-251-3-3-0-28 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - Leveil, [ca 1977]; F-251-3-3-0-29 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - CAPRI (Committee Against Political Repression in India statement), 1977 - 1978; F-251-3-3-0-30 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - IPANA Public Statements, 1977 - 1979; F-251-3-3-0-31 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - Subscriptions to India, 1977 - 1979; F-251-3-3-0-32 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - P. Dhillon: "In Defence of the Genuine Communist Party of India", 1978; F-251-3-3-0-33 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - League: Canadian Imperialism RSC, 1978; F-251-3-3-0-34 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - Vancouver: Sending Funds to India, 1978; F-251-3-3-0-35 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - More on "Discussions with In Struggle", 1978; F-251-3-3-0-36 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - Hari Sharma: Let's Make the Montreal Convention a Convention of Consolidation and Strength, 1978; F-251-3-3-0-37 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - IPANA Convention 1978: Solidarity Messages, F-251-3-3-0-38 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - Montreal Convention (minutes, press releases, resolutions, reports, etc.), 1978; F-251-3-3-0-39 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - Funds and Resources, 1978 - 1979; F-251-3-3-0-40 (Archival box - standard 251-24)
    - IPANA Study Circles, 1979; F-251-3-3-0-41 (Archival box - standard 251-25)
    - Vancouver Unit, 1978 - 1980; F-251-3-3-0-42 (Archival box - standard 251-25)
    - Evaluation of Vancouver Unit, 1978 - 1982; F-251-3-3-0-43 (Archival box - standard 251-25)
    - IPANA: Letters, memos to executive and central office, etc., 1979 - 1984; F-251-3-3-0-44 (Archival box - standard 251-25)
    - IPANA Units / Members, [ca 1980]; F-251-3-3-0-45 (Archival box - standard 251-25)
    - IPANA: The Sekhar Affair - September 1981, 1981 - 1982; F-251-3-3-0-46 (Archival box - standard 251-25)
    - IPANA Vancouver contacts, 1981 - 1982; F-251-3-3-0-47 (Archival box - standard 251-25)
    - IPANA Vancouver Unit Meeting (communications), 1980 - 1982; F-251-3-3-0-48 (Archival box - standard 251-25)
    - IPANA - communication to units, 1980 - 1982; F-251-3-3-0-49 (Archival box - standard 251-25)
    - Samaanta, 1981 - 1983; F-251-3-3-0-50 (Archival box - standard 251-26)
    - Trade Unions and India (correspondence), 1982; F-251-3-3-0-51 (Archival box - standard 251-26)
    - IPANA Central Office Communication, 1982; F-251-3-3-0-52 (Archival box - standard 251-26)
    - Vancouver Unit, 1982 - 1983; F-251-3-3-0-53 (Archival box - standard 251-26)
    - Regarding Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1983; F-251-3-3-0-54 (Archival box - standard 251-26)
    - Gursharan Singh (trip to Vancouver), 1983; F-251-3-3-0-55 (Archival box - standard 251-26)
    - Petition: Dual Citizenship for Overseas Indians, [ca 1983]; F-251-3-3-0-56 (Archival box - standard 251-26)
    - On IPANA's Political Practice and Its Political Orientation, 1984; F-251-3-3-0-57 (Archival box - standard 251-26)
    - IPANA: Important documents, 1983 - 1985; F-251-3-3-0-58 (Archival box - standard 251-26)